Guide to the Ethel May Gate Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ethel May Gate papers, 1912-1940.
GEN MSS 250
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.09
(5 boxes)
Includes typescript and holograph manuscripts of Gate's collections of stories and poems for children, including "Punch & Robinetta", "The Fortunate Days", and "Tales from the Enchanted Isles", among others. Other writings include the essay collection "The Harvest of the Years" and individual short stories, poems, novels, and plays, including two acts completing Sir James M. Barrie's unfinished play, "Shall We Join the Ladies?". Also in the collection are actors' annotated copies of many of the plays, a letter from Joan Luxton, a personal reflection concerning Gate's father, and manuscript copies of four nineteenth century songs.
Gate, Ethel May
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of Ethel May Gate, 1946.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains literary manuscripts of the English writer Ethel May Gate (1882?-1942). A small number of other papers are also included. The collection is organized into two series, Writings and Other Papers, and spans the dates 1912-1940.
Series I, Writings, contains two subseries. The first, "Anthologies," includes manuscripts and typescripts for several of the author's collections of children's stories and poems, including Punch and Robinetta, The Fortunate Days, and Tales from the Enchanted Isles, among others, and the essay collection The Harvest of the Years. The second subseries, "Other Writings," includes manuscripts and typescripts of short stories, poems, novels and plays, as well as actors' annotated copies of scripts for many of the plays. Also included is a typescript of two acts completing Sir James M. Barrie's unfinished play, "Shall We Join the Ladies."
Series II, Other Papers, includes a letter from Joan Luxton, a tally of expenses, a personal reflection concerning the author's father, and copies of four nineteenth century popular songs.
Authors, English -- Archives; All the king's trumpets; Harvest of the years; Punch & Robinetta; Shall we join the ladies?; Tales from the enchanted isles; Tales from the secret kingdom; Fortunate days; Barrie, J. M. (James Matthew), 1860-1937 ( Shall we join the ladies?); Gate, Ethel May; Luxton, Joan
- WRITINGS, 1912-1940; Series I; 2.05; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Writings, is organized into two subseries: Anthologies and Other Writings. Each subseries is arranged alphabetically by title. Individual pieces within anthologies are also arranged alphabetically, with the exception of poetry, which may be found at the end of the anthology in which it appeared.
  - ANTHOLOGIES
    - The Fortunate Days
      - Note: This anthology and Punch and Robinetta were originally conceived as one volume. For typescript of this larger, unpublished version See: Punch and Robinetta
      - Typescript for the anthology, corrected, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - "The Castle of Delight," autograph, 1920 Jul 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - manuscript
      - "The Fortunate Days," autograph, 1920 Aug 20 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - manuscript of title story, signed
      - "The Golden Horseshoe," autograph, 1919 Jun 7 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - manuscript, signed
      - "The Story of the Learned Man,", 1920 Sep 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - autograph manuscript, signed
      - Poems from "The Fortunate Days" (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Autograph manuscripts and drafts, including "The Enchanted Isle," "Hard Times," "Under the Ground," and "You and Me." Included also, on the verso of an "Enchanted Isle" draft, is "The Foundling," not published in this anthology, and on the same leaf with "Under the Ground," "The Ball," which was published in her anthology Punch and Robinetta.
        For other drafts of "You and Me" and "Under the Ground"
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Punch and Robinetta, box 1, folder 20
    - The Harvest of the Years: Six Essays
      - 2 typescripts, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - "On a Looking Glass," autograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - manuscript
      - "On Perfection (Being the Last of the, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Little Girl)," autograph manuscript
      - "On a Spider," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Punch and Robinetta
      - Title Page and Table of Contents (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Autograph manuscript fragment of early draft, before the anthology was split into two volumes
      - Carbon typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Early version before the split into two volumes
      - Typescript and galleys, corrected, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Anthology as published, after the split into two volumes
      - "The Fairy Shoemaker," autograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - manuscript
      - "The Princess Dyonetia," autograph, 1920 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - manuscript
      - "Punch and Robinetta," autograph (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - manuscript of title story, corrected, signed
      - "The Tapestry Prince," autograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - manuscript, corrected
      - "The Two Poor Seamstresses"
        - Autograph manuscript, 1920 Mar 19 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Poems from Punch and Robinetta, 1920, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Autograph manuscripts and drafts of "The Ball," "The Minstrel," "The Talisman," "Raspberry Tarts," and "The Return." Also includes drafts of poems published in The Fortunate Days, and "The Lovely One," not published in either volume. For another draft of "The Ball"
        See: The Fortunate Days, box 1, folder 6
    - Tales from the Enchanted Isles
      - Title Page and Table of Contents (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - autograph draft and manuscript
      - Carbon typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Typescript and illustration proofs (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - "The Enchanted Galleon," autograph, 1925 Jul 24 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - manuscript
      - "The Good Queen's Son," autograph, 1922 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - manuscript, signed
      - "The King's Sceptre," autograph, 1923 Jul 23 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - manuscript, signed
      - "The Lamp from Fairyland," autograph, 1923 Oct 27 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - manuscript, signed
      - "Proper and Right," autograph, 1925 Aug 2 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - manuscript
      - "The Singing Water," autograph, 1924 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - manuscript
      - "The Tree of Stone," autograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - manuscript
      - Poems from Tales from the Enchanted Isles, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31)
        Autograph manuscripts of "The Adventure," "The Curiosity Shop," "The Golden Violet," "Great News," "The Harper," and "The Song of the Fountain"
    - Tales from the Secret Kingdom
      - Typescript, revised and corrected (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - "The Fog Princess: a Fairy Story,", 1918 Mar 11 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - autograph manuscript, signed
    - Tales of the Italian Renaissance
      "The Banker's Daughter" [Story]
      See also: "The Banker's Daughter" [Play], box 3, folder 42
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - "Born Under Taurus" [Story]
        See also: "Born Under Taurus" [Play], box 3, folder 43
        - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 36)
        - Typescript, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - "The Duchess Diverts her Lord with an Old Wives Tale," carbon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - typescript, incomplete
  - OTHER WRITINGS
    - "The Admiral's Lady: An Extravaganza of Napoleonic Times," autograph, [1940?] Nov (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - manuscript, signed
      - A, play in one act; 36 leaves of a red
      - exercise book; author's address at Morcambe on cover
    - [All the King's Trumpets], typescript, corrected (Box 2, Folder 40)
      p. 99a inserted after p. 99 and p. 110 numbered 110 and 111
      See also: "To the Sound of Trumpets," box 5, folder 97
    - "The Bale of Merchandise," autograph (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - manuscript
    - "The Banker's Daughter" [Play], 1937 Sep 28 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - autograph manuscript
      See also: short story of the same title, box 2, folder 34
    - "Born Under Taurus" [Play], autograph, 1937 Jul 11 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - manuscript
      Note on t.p. "Based on short story in Oct-Dec. 1925 number of The Boomerang."
      See: box 2, folder 36
    - "Brilliantina, or Our Wildest Dreams: an Extravaganza", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
      A play, part hectographed (?) and part mimeographed
    - "Constancy," autograph manuscript, 1919 May 2 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - signed
      Note at top of p. 1: (Reprinted by permission of "The Woman's Leader")
    - "The Curtain"
      - Autograph manuscript; signed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Typed manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "The Drinking Cup," autograph, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "Enquire Within: A Play in One Act"
      - Carbon typescript, corrected, signed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
        In folder, with title and author's name and address on front cover, and note (Copyright by the author)
      - Typescript, corrected (incomplete), n.d. (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Typescript labeled "Prompt Copy," corrected, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 51)
        In brown paper folder, with blue spine with title and author's name and address on front cover, and note "The fee for each performance of this play is one guinea, payable to the author in advance"
      - 3 mimeographed copies, with, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - manuscript corrections and additions
      - Typescripts of the individual parts of the 4 main characters (Box 3, Folder 53)
        4 main characters: The Young Lady, First Enquiry Officer, Second Enquiry Officer, and The Young Airman; in 4 small folders
    - "Epitaph for Lucrezia"
      - Autograph manuscript of a play in one act, signed and dated, 1936 Jun 19 (Box 3, Folder 54)
      - Carbon typescript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
        Inscribed "Please return to Miss Hartley, [...] Munwell Hill, London."
    - "Folly and Discretion, or What Jane Left Untold (A Jane Austin Trifle in One Act)", 1932 Aug 21
      - Autograph manuscript, signed and dated, 1932 Aug 21 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - 2 typescripts (1 carbon), with manuscript corrections, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
        First copy in brown paper folder
      - 2 carbon typescripts, with notes, 1932 Aug 21 (Box 3, Folder 58)
      - and sketches
        In brown paper covers; both bear name and address of Miss H. D. Hartley, Regent's Park, London; one is dated on the last page
      - 6 carbon typescripts, annotated, 1932 Aug 21 (Box 3, Folder 59)
        In brown paper covers; with notes [by actors?]; two bear the author's name and address, Makepeace Avenue, Highgate; four are dated on the last page
    - "The Fountain"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, 1921 Jan 12 (Box 3, Folder 60)
      - Typescript, corrected, with manuscript title page, signed, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - "The Frozen Princess: Fairy Play in Three Acts," autograph manuscript, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - signed
      In exercise book with loose page laid in; possibly based on short story of the same title in the anthology The Broom Fairies, 1917
    - "Der Gevatter Tod: Ein Schauspiel in Einem Akt aus der Deutschen Romantik Nach Grimm's Marchen"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, 1936 Feb 12 (Box 4, Folder 63)
        Working title: "Der Gevatter Tod: Phantasiestuck in Einem Akt Mit Prolog"
      - Autograph manuscript of prologue, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 64)
      - 2 carbon typescripts, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 65)
        With manuscript corrections and additions; attached to the carbon copy is a list of names and addresses, apparently of people who took part in a performance of this play
      - Manuscript copy in English, signed, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 66)
        Titled "Godfather Death: A Play in One Act with Prologue, Founded on Grimm's Fairy Tale Der Gevatter Tod"; in writing tablet; 28 p. of other dramatic material in pencil, in back of tablet
    - "In Search of Her Youth (Synopsis)"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 67)
      - Typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 68)
        With one page in manuscript
    - "The Knotted Willows," autograph, 1920 Jun 26 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - manuscript, signed
      At head of title: "Reprinted by permission of 'The Woman's Leader'"
    - "Meriting Attention," typescript, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - signed, corrected
    - "The Net: A Tragic Episode"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, 1927 Jul 17 (Box 4, Folder 71)
        In brown paper folder, with title, and author's name and address on front cover
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 72)
        Note on first leaf: "Copyright by the Author in 1928"; in gray paper folder, with title, and author's name and address on front cover
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, of the "full version", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
        In black paper folder, with title, author's name and address on front cover
      - Typescript with manuscript corrections and additions (Box 4, Folder 74)
        In brown paper folder, with title on front cover
      - Typescripts of the individual parts of the five main characters (Box 4, Folder 75)
        Characters: Rosina, Alessandro de'Medici, Caterina de'Pazzi, Lorenzino, Palacia de'Pazzi; in 5 small separate folders
    - "Once Upon a Time," typescript with, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - manuscript corrections
      A play in two acts; author's name and address on verso of last page
    - "Perfect Bliss: A Christmas Mystery"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Typescript, with author's manuscript corrections (Box 4, Folder 78)
    - "The Polite Shepherd of Manor Gardens:, 1929 Nov 16 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    - An Episode of the Arcadian Civil Service," autograph manuscript, signed
    - "A Portrait by Kneller," autograph, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 80)
    - manuscript
      Play in one act; in brown paper folder, with title, author's name, and address on front cover; with newspaper clipping
    - "The Portrait of the Madonna,", 1916 Nov 26 (Box 4, Folder 81)
    - autograph manuscript, signed
    - "The Potter's Wheel," autograph, 1912 Jul 6 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "Queen Flora's Garden," autograph, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - manuscript, signed
      Considered for but not included in Punch and Robinetta
      See: Box 1, folder 11
    - "Queen Flora Ruled the Flowers,", n.d. (Box 4, Folder 84)
    - autograph manuscript of poem
      Addressed to Mrs. Risley, Hastings
    - "The Secret Room," autograph, 1923 Nov 28 (Box 4, Folder 85)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "Shall We Join the Ladies"
      - Typescript, with corrections, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 86)
        Two acts completing Sir James Barrie's unfinished play of the same name; in green paper folder, with title, author's name and address on front cover in author's autograph
      - Mimeographed copy of Sir James Barrie's unfinished play, [1925] (Box 5, Folder 87)
        Issued from the office of Elizabeth Marbury with the terms of the contest offering a prize of $1,000 for the best completion of the play; in blue folder, with title, announcement of the prize, etc., on front cover
    - "Something Gorgeous," autograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "The Story of the Cid," autograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "Strange and Beautiful," autograph, 1940 Dec 8 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "The String of Beads," autograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - manuscript
    - "Tales from Ariel's Isle," autograph, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - manuscript of "Forward"
      See also: Tales from the Enchanted Isles, box 1, folder 21
    - "Teaching Us All a Lesson," 2 type-, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - scripts with manuscript corrections
      With 2 rejection slips
    - A Thing of Beauty, n.d.
      - Autograph manuscript; in 8 thin, blue exercise books (Box 5, Folder 94-95)
      - Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 96)
        Accompanied by a printed announcement issued by Hodder & Stoughton, concerning a prize of one thousand guineas in a novel competition; also, a copy of a letter (dated 1916 Mar 27), in Miss Gate's hand, addressed from her to Hodder & Stoughton entering her novel, A Thing of Beauty, in the contest
    - "To the Sound of Trumpets: A Fairy Play in Three Acts," typescript, corrected (Box 5, Folder 97)
      Note in author's hand on leaf 1: "All the King's Trumpets, published simultaneously in Gt. Britain & the U.S.A. by Basil Blackwell, Oxford, & the Yale University Press, New Haven & New York, is based upon this play by the same author;" promotional material from both publishers for that work included on paper cover
      See: Box 2, folder 40
    - "The Unknown Princess," autograph, 1933 Nov 4 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - manuscript
    - "The Upholding Arms," autograph, 1924 Jun 9 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - manuscript, signed
    - "The Window," autograph manuscript (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - "Within the House of God the Priest has hung," autograph poem, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 101)
      On a brown wrapper for typing paper
    - "The Wonderful Journey: A Fairy Play for Grown-Ups in 4 Acts and a Prologue"
      Note: Gate published a story of the same title in Tales from the Secret Kingdom, 1919
      - Autograph manuscript, scenario only, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 102)
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 103)
      - Typescript (carbon) with manuscript corrections, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 104)
- OTHER PAPERS, 1935-1938; Series II; 4
  - Luxton, Joan. ANS to Ethel May Gate, [London], 1935 Jul 17 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - [Dream of Her Father], autograph, 1938 Oct 25 (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - manuscript
    Gate's reflections on a dream about her father, who died in 1889
  - Autograph account of expenses, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Manuscript copies of 4 songs, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 108)
    Songs include "I Remember" [Charles Zeuner, 1830?], "Pestal" by W.H. Bellamy, arranged by C.E. Horn, 1845, "Villikins and his Dinah" [from burlesque by F. C. Burnand], 1855, and "The Songs of Long Ago; air: Auld Scotia's Sangs, John Thompson"; in grey paper folder with titles on front cover and Miss Gate's name and address inside front cover